A Guide to the Secretary of the Commonwealth, Records, 1865-1872
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records, 1865-1872
Library of Virginia
38130
1.7 cubic feet
Secretary of the Commonwealth
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information available.
Historical Information
The Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth has evolved from early colonial times when there existed a Secretary of the Colony. Thomas Nelson held the position of the first Secretary of Virginia in 1776. Early Secretaries were elected by the public. An Act of the General Assembly in 1920 changed the election to a joint vote of the General Assembly. In a 1930 Act the duties of the Secretary were redefined with the Secretary of the Commonwealth serving as the ex officio secretary of the Governor, as custodian of many official State records, and as keeper of the Greater and Lesser Seals of the Commonwealth. The office of the Secretary has gradually acquired other functions, such as: service of out-of-state civil process; appointment and regulation of notaries public; and registration and oversight of lobbyists. The Office became a gubernational appointment subsequent to a 1958 Act of the Assembly. The Secretary of the Commonwealth is under the jurisdiction of the Governor's Office.
The Secretary is appointed by the Governor for a term of four years. The Secretary has an Executive assistant and an Assistant who is in charge of prison mail and research duties. The Chief Clerk is responsible for the Governor's Journal and extraditions and acts as general office manager. Major activities are: serving as ex officio Secretary to the Governor; serving as the keeper of the seals of the Commonwealth; compiling and publishing the annual Blue Book; commissioning and regulating notary publics, including the publication of a Notary Handbook and conduct of disciplinary hearings; promulgating the lobbying disclosure requirements, registration of lobbyst, and recording of lobbying reports; servicing the civil process of out-of-state defendants and other parties; and authenticating and certifying the records of the courts and of any state agency.
Scope and Content Information
I. General correspondence, 1865. This series includes routine correspondence addressed to the Secretary of the Commonwealth, as well as correspondence addressed to Governor Pierpont and referred to the Secretary. Also includes some outgoing correspondence of Governor Pierpont. Much of the routine correspondence is in relation to appointments, resignations, pardons, elections, and state publications. Some noteworthy correspondence in this series includes: letter from Gov. Pierpont to the General Assembly re: irregularities in the conduct of the Board of Directors of the Eastern Lunatic Asylum (Jan. 10, 1865); appointment and oath of the Secretary of the Commonwealth (Apr. 1, 1865); inventory of the Executive Mansion (June 2, 1865); letter from Gov. Pierpont to the Board of Visitors of the Institution for the Deaf, Dumb and Blind in Staunton, Va. re: treatment of pupils by the Superintendent (June 7, 1865); letter to Gov. Pierpont from the Superintendent of the State Penitentiary (Aug. 9, 1865); letter from Gov. Pierpont re: revocation of authorization to pilots (Sept. 10, 1865); circular from the Secretary of the Commonwealth to county justices regarding indigent white persons in their districts (Sept. 12, 1865) - reponses from justices occur over the next several months; special report of the Superintendent of the Western Asylum (Oct. 17, 1865); copy of the charter of the Southern Union Telegraph Co. (Nov. 9, 1865); letter from U.S. Secretary of the Interior William Seward re: ratification of amendment against slavery (Nov. 18, 1865); letter from Gov. Pierpont to the House of Delegates re: death of Littleton W. Tazewell (Dec. 5, 1865); letter from Gov. Pierpont to the General Assembly re: Day of Thanksgiving (Dec. 6, 1865); letter from Gov. Pierpont to the General Assembly re: State Penitentiary guards (Dec. 13, 1865); letter from Gov. Pierpont to Maj. Gen. Terry re: protection of white citizens in southern and eastern Virginia (December 11, 1865); letter from Gov. Pierpont to Hon. Hugh McCullough, U.S. Secretary of the Treasury re: collection of taxes in Virginia (Dec. 20, 1865).
II. Qualifications, 1865. This series includes qualification documentation for various positions, including judges, commissioners of deeds, inspectors, Sheriff for the City of Richmond, Penitentiary Storekeeper, Harbor Master for the Port of Richmond, Commissioner of Wrecks for Northampton Co., and Inspector of the Public Guard.
III. Proclamations, 1865. Includes three proclamations by Gov. Pierpont: 1865 Sept. 1 re: shall the General Assembly be given power to alter or amend the third article of the Consitution of Virginia; 1865 Nov. 3 re: authorizing the Circuit Court of the City of Richmond to be held in the Capitol; 1865 Dec. 17 re: location of the Wise Co. Courthouse.
IV. Notary Public applications, recommendations and qualifications, 1865.
V. General correspondence, 1866-1872. This series contains the routine correspondence of the Secretary of the Commonwealth regarding appointments, pardons, elections, seals, notaries public and state publications.
VI. Oaths of allegiance, 1870.
VII. Articles of agreement and bonds, 1870-1871. This series includes articles of agreement and bonds for printing and for ruling and binding of state publications.
VIII. Receipts for state publications, 1871. This series consists of letters of receipt for Virginia state publications (Acts of the General Assembly, etc.) from Virginia localities and from other states.
IX. Miscellaneous records, 1865-1872 (oversize). These records include: Governor's message to the General Assembly (printed) (June 19, 1865); Demands from Governors of other states for fugitives from justice (1865); and Blank forms from other states, c. 1865-1872.
Organization
Organized into the following nine (9) series: I. General correspondence, 1865; II. Qualifications, 1865; III. Proclamations, 1876; IV. Notary Public applications, recommendations and qualifications, 1865; V. General correspondence, 1866-1871; VI. Oaths of allegiance, 1870; VII. Articles of agreement and bonds, 1870-1871; VIII. Receipts for state publications, 1871; IX. Miscellaneous records, 1865-1872.
Contents List
- Series I: General correspondence, 1865
  Arranged chronologically by month.
  - Correspondence, 1865 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1865 March (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1865 April (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1865 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1865 June (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1865 July (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1865 August (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1865 September (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1865 October (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1865 November (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1865 December (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II: Qualifications, 1865
  Arranged chronologically by year.
  - Qualifications, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series III: Proclamations, 1865
  - Proclamations, 1865 September 11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Proclamations, 1865 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Proclamations, 1865 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Notary Public applications, recommendations and qualifications, 1865
  - Notary Public, 1865 June (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Notary Public, 1865 July (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Notary Public, 1865 August (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Notary Public, 1865 September (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Notary Public, 1865 October (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notary Public, 1865 November (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Notary Public, 1865 December (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series V: General Correspondence, 1866-1871
  - Correspondence, 1866 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1867 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1868 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1869 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1871 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1872 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series VI: Oaths of allegiance, 1870
  Arranged by year.
  - Oaths, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series VII: Articles of agreement and bonds, 1870-1871
  Arranged by folder title.
  - Articles of agreement and bonds for printing, 1870-1871 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Articles of agreement and bonds for ruling and binding, 1870-1871 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Series VIII: Receipts for state publications from localities, 1871
  - Receipts for state publications from localities, 1871 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Receipts for state publications from other states, 1871 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Series IX: Miscellaneous records, 1865-1872
  - Governor's message to the General Assembly, 1865 June 19 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Demands from Governors of other states for fugitives from justice, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Blank forms from other states-Illinois, c. 1865-1872 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Blank forms from other states-Massachusetts, c. 1865-1872 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Blank forms from other states-New York, c. 1865-1872 (Box 4, Folder 5)